Tian Kang

Ph.D. candidate

Department of Biomedical Informatics, Columbia University

E-mail: <u>tk2624@cumc.columbia.edu</u> Phone: 917-288-9570

Address: 622 West 168 Street, New York, NY 10032

DISSERTATION SUMMARY

My Ph.D. dissertation title is "Machine Reading Comprehension for Medical Evidence". The research aims to bridge the gaps of information need for Evidence-based Medicine in a timely manner by developing a novel attention model for Machine Reading Comprehension that is interpretable and informed by extracted domain knowledge, and eventually enabling efficient question answering for clinical decision making.

EDUCATIONS

Ph.D. in Biomedical Informatics, Columbia University, 2021 (anticipated), advised by Dr. Chunhua Weng	GPA 3.90/4.00
M.A. in Biomedical informatics, Columbia University, 2016	GPA 3.76/4.00
B.S. in Bioinformatics, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, China, 2014	GPA 3.50/4.00

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

A PICO-informed Self-Attention model for Machine Reading Comprehension for medical evidence.

Department of Biomedical Informatics, Columbia University, March 2020 - now

• Developing a novel attention model for Machine Reading Comprehension that is interpretable and informed by extracted domain knowledge.

Improving PICO Element Recognition by UMLS-based Data Augmentation

Department of Biomedical Informatics, Columbia University, Dec. 2019 - March 2020

- Developing a data augmentation method, called UMLS-EDA, by simple text transformation and incorporation of domain knowledge such as UMLS, is effective in helping improve both PICO element recognition tasks in both entity and sentence level.
- Proposed UMLS-EDA improved the biLSTM-CRF model significantly. By adding BERT into the model, the model achieved state-of-the-art performance.

Knowledge Representation of Medical Evidence based on PICO framework for PubMed Literatures

Department of Biomedical Informatics, Columbia University, Nov. 2018 – now

• Developing an information extraction system for fully standardizing medical abstracts (Named Entity Recognition, study arm resolution, relation identification, etc.) to facilitate Evidence-Based Medicine and information retrieval for PubMed.

Cataloging and mapping treatments for patients from an Online Autism Community

Department of Biomedical Informatics, Columbia University, Sep. 2016 – Jan. 2017

- Applied NLP to understand the treatments used in real world for Autism Spectrum Disorder using patient-generated text from online health communities and compared it to treatment guidelines.
- Wrote the manuscript and presented it in 2017 WWW conference.

EliIE (Free-text Eligibility Criteria Information Extraction System): A machine learning-based IE system to formalize clinical research eligibility criteria into OMOP Common Data Model

Department of Biomedical Informatics, Columbia University, Aug. 2015 - Apr. 2016

- Lead an annotation team, designed annotation guidelines and created training data of clinical trial eligibility criteria.
- Developed an IE system called EliIE applying NLP techniques and machine learning approach to parse and formalize clinical trial eligibility criteria in order to facilitate trial recruitment.(GitHub repository: https://github.com/Tian312/EliIE)
- Wrote the manuscript and presented the paper at JAMIA Journal Club Invited Talk.

Detecting Speculations and Negations in Chinese Clinical Notes using Character and Word Embedding

Department of Biomedical Informatics, Columbia University, Aug. 2015 - Dec. 2015

- Explored how Word Embedding can improve Chinese clinical NLP tasks. Both speculation and negation detection results achieved the state of the art when the project completed.
- Wrote both manuscripts.

Readability Assessment of Clinical Trial Eligibility Criteria

Department of Biomedical Informatics, Columbia University, Oct. 2014 – Feb. 2015

- Assessed readability of the world's largest online clinical trial registry clincialtrials.gov using NLP techniques to evaluate its accessibility to health consumers.
- Wrote the manuscripts and presented the paper in AMIA 2015.

PUBLICATIONS

- o **Kang, T.,** Zou, S. and Weng, C., 2019. Pretraining to Recognize PICO Elements from Randomized Controlled Trial Literature. *Studies in health technology and informatics*, 264, pp.188-192.
- Wei, D.H., Kang, T., Pincus, H.A. and Weng, C., 2019. Construction of Disease Similarity Networks Using Concept Embedding and Ontology. Studies in health technology and informatics, 264, pp.442-446.
- o Rogers, JR, Callahan, TJ, **Kang, T**, Bauck, A, Khare, R, Brown, JS, Kahn, MG and Weng, C 2019 A Data Element-Function Conceptual Model for Data Quality Checks. *eGEMs* (*Generating Evidence & Methods to improve patient outcomes*), 7(1): 17, pp. 1–14.
- O Yuan, C., Ryan, P.B., Ta, C., Guo, Y., Li, Z., Hardin, J., Makadia, R., Jin, P., Shang, N., **Kang, T.** and Weng, C., 2019. Criteria2Query: a natural language interface to clinical databases for cohort definition. *Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association*.
- Butler, A., Wei, W., Yuan, C., Kang, T., Si, Y. and Weng, C., 2018. The Data Gap in the EHR for Clinical Research Eligibility Screening. AMIA Summits on Translational Science Proceedings, 2017, p.320
- Sen, A., Goldstein, A., Chakrabarti, S., Shang, N., Kang, T., Yaman, A., Ryan, P.B. and Weng, C., 2017. The representativeness of eligible patients in type 2 diabetes trials: a case study using GIST 2.0. *Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association*.
- o Zhang, S., **Kang, T.,** Qiu, L., Zhang, W., Yu, Y. and Elhadad, N. and Weng, C., 2017, April. Cataloguing Treatments Discussed and Used in Online Autism Communities. *In Proceedings of the 26th International Conference on World Wide Web (pp. 123-131)*. International World Wide Web Conferences Steering Committee.
- Kang, T., Zhang, S., Tang, Y., Hruby, G.W., Rusanov, A., Elhadad, N. and Weng, C., 2017. EliIE: An open-source information extraction system for clinical trial eligibility criteria. *Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association*, 24(6), pp.1062-1071.
- o **Kang, T.**, Zhang, S., Xu, N., Wen, D., Zhang, X. and Lei, J., 2017. Detecting negation and scope in Chinese clinical notes using character and word embedding. *Computer methods and programs in biomedicine*, 140, pp.53-59.
- o Zhou, F., Cao, H., Zuo, X., Zhang, T., Zhang, X., et al., 2016. Deep sequencing of the MHC region in the Chinese population contributes to studies of complex disease. *Nature genetics*, 48(7), p.740.
- O Zhang, S., **Kang, T.**, Zhang, X., Wen, D., Elhadad, N. and Lei, J., 2016. Speculation detection for Chinese clinical notes: impacts of word segmentation and embedding models. *Journal of biomedical informatics*, 60, pp.334-341.
- o **Kang, T.,** Elhadad, N. and Weng, C., 2015. Initial readability assessment of clinical trial eligibility criteria. *In AMIA Annual Symposium Proceedings* (Vol. 2015, p. 687). American Medical Informatics Association.

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

Paper Pretraining to Recognize PICO Elements from Randomized Controlled Trial Literature. MEDINFO 2019, Lyon, France.

Paper Cataloguing treatments discussed and used in online autism communities, 2017 International World Wide Web Conference (WWW), Perth, Australia.

Paper We make choices we think are going to save us": Debate and stance identification for online breast cancer CAM discussions, 2017 International World Wide Web Conference (WWW), Perth, Australia.

Paper Initial Readability Assessment of Clinical Trial Eligibility Criteria, AMIA Annual Symposium 2015, San Francisco, CA.